<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An evident demonstration to Gods elect which clearly manifesteth to them I. How necessary and expedient it is for them to come to witnesse true faith, II. That after they have attained to the faith, it must be tried as gold is tried in the fire, III. It shews how many have departed from the faith and denied it, IV. That the standing of the saints is by faith in the Son of God, V. How strong Abraham was in the faith and how all that believe are to look unto him / by Margret Fell.</title>
            <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36425</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15690519</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15690519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104398</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1592:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An evident demonstration to Gods elect which clearly manifesteth to them I. How necessary and expedient it is for them to come to witnesse true faith, II. That after they have attained to the faith, it must be tried as gold is tried in the fire, III. It shews how many have departed from the faith and denied it, IV. That the standing of the saints is by faith in the Son of God, V. How strong Abraham was in the faith and how all that believe are to look unto him / by Margret Fell.</title>
                  <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata sheet bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104398:1"/>
            <p>AN EVIDENT DEMONSTRATION TO Gods Elect, VVhich clearly manifeſteth to them,
<list>
                  <item>I. How neceſſary and expedient it is for them to come to witneſſe true faith.</item>
                  <item>II. That after they have attained to the faith, it muſt be tried as gold is tried in the fire.</item>
                  <item>III. It ſhews how many have departed from the faith and denied it.</item>
                  <item>IV. That the ſtanding of the Saints is by faith in the Son of God.</item>
                  <item>V. How ſtrong Abraham was in the faith, and how all that believe are to look unto him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Margret Fell.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>That the trial of your faith being much more precious then of gold that periſheth, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, <bibl>1 Pet. 1.7.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the victory that overcometh the World even our faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the ſigne of the Bull and Mouth near Alderſgate, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104398:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104398:2"/>
            <head>Friends of God and of the Living Truth as it is in Jeſus, who are called to be Saints and to live godly in Chriſt Jeſus as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Saints.</head>
            <p>THere is ſomething upon me as from the Lord to write unto you concerning the precious Faith which was once delivered unto the Saints, which (may be) you may be called to contend for; times of tryal thereof ſeeming to approach; but the the onely intent and deſire of my ſoul is, that you may be brought into it, in the Truth and ſoundneſſe of it, which indeed is a myſtery, and cannot be held but in a pure conſcience void of offence towards God and towards man: And being that it is ſo, that without faith it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pleaſe God, and that whatſoever is not of faith is ſin; This being weighed and read in the pure eternal Light which every one hath a meaſure of to try withal, it will nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern every one to ſearch and try narrowly and throughly, whether they be in the faith which is of Gods Elect yea or no: This may be lightly looked upon with many, as though it were needleſſe and below their condition and ſtate, as if it were eaſie to be in the faith of God, yea the very World the Apoſtatized Chriſtians will talk of a faith though it be dead and they yet in their ſins; But truly Friends I ſee in the Eternal that it is a great myſtery to be made partaker of the precious faith, which gives the victory over the World, and faith is the gift of God.</p>
            <p>And I find in the Scriptures of the Prophets that there was few that witneſſed and ſpoke of Faith, though there was many faithful men which by faith obtained a good report, and died in the faith, by which they did the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, according to his Eternal purpoſe, yet the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were under the cloud, and the appearance of God in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104398:3"/>
their day was in a cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea, <hi>and were all baptized unto Moſes in the cloud and in the Sea, and they did drink of the Rock which followed them, which Rock was Chriſt;</hi> while <hi>Moſes</hi> is Read the vail is over the heart, which vail is done away in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>When God called <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> he ſaid, Hear now my word, if there be a Prophet among you, I the Lord will make my ſelf known unto him in a viſion, and ſpeak unto him in a dream. This is the ſtate which we muſt paſſe through; but the Lord ſaid <hi>with Moſes my ſervant it is not ſo, who is faithful in all my houſe, with him I will ſpeak mouth to mouth, even apparently and not in dark ſpeeches.</hi> Here <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful to God as a ſervant, and his miniſtration was glorious, yet this glory was to be done away, by reaſon of the glory that excelled, which glory remains where the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is the covering. And ſo, Friends, come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Light of the Son of God, which gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, the brightnes of the Fathers glory, which <hi>Moſes</hi> could not ſee and live; And here you will come to ſee &amp; to read through the myſtery of the faith of the Goſpel in the miniſtration of the ſpirit; And now that none may think of themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what they ought to think, let every one with the light of Jeſus ſeriouſly and ſinglely ſearch and try your ſtanding, for it may be that times of tryal of faith may come. The Apoſtle bad the <hi>Corinthians</hi> examine themſelves whether they were in the faith, <hi>prove your own ſelves</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>know you not how that Chriſt is in you except you be Reprobates:</hi> This he ſaid to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> who were a gathered people, And to the <hi>Galathians</hi> ſaith he, <hi>If a man think of himſelf to be ſomething when he is nothing he deceives himſelf, but let every man prove his own work, and then he will have joy in himſelf and not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, be not offended that you are put to a ſearch and warned before-hand, that your foundation and ſtanding may be ſure when the day of tryal comes, for the Lord hath ſaid <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.9. <hi>I will bring the third part of them through the fire, and will refine them as ſilver is refined, and try them as gold
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104398:3"/>
is tryed, And they ſhall call on my Name, and I will hear them, I will ſay it is my people, and they ſhall ſay the Lord is my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith <hi>Ye who are kept by the power of God through the faith unto ſalvation ready to be revealed in the laſt time, wherein ye greatly rejoyce, though now for a ſeaſon ye are in heavineſſe through manifold temptations, that the tryal of your faith being much more precious then gold that periſheth though it be tried by fire might be found unto the praiſe, honour and glory at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> O bleſſed will ye be if you be found here, for then will you not think it ſtrange concerning the fiery tryalls which are to try you, but you will even rejoyce, inaſmuch as you are partakers of the ſufferings of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Truly Friends my care is, with the deſire of my ſoul, that you might come into the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and that the ſame mind may be in you that was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus, who made himſelf of no reputation, but took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men, and being found in faſhion as a man he humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and became obedient to the death of the Croſſe, and through that he is exalted; And this is the path that the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus muſt walk in, wch may be found ſtrait and narrow to the firſt man which is rough and hairy, <hi>Eſau</hi>-like: And though (as I ſaid before) you may think ſtrange that you ſhould be exhorted to come into the faith of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, yet this is above the Diſciples condition, for they were often reproved for the want of this of their Lord and Maſter, when he was exhorting them to take no thought for their meat nor for their drink, neither for their body what they ſhould put on, for ſaith he <hi>ſhall he not much more clothe you O ye of little faith.</hi> And again when the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt roſe upon the Sea, they begun to be afraid, Then ſaid he unto them, <hi>Why are ye fearful O ye of little faith?</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain when he ſhewed them the Fig-tree how it was withered, Chriſt ſaid unto them, <hi>If ye have faith and doubt not, ye ſhall not onely do this which is done to this Fig-tree, but alſo if you ſay unto this mountain be thou removed into the Sea, and it ſhall be done, and whatſoever you pray for, believing, ye ſhall receive.</hi> And again he ſaid unto <hi>Peter</hi> when the Sea was boiſtrous and he afraid, he ſaid unto him, <hi>O thou of little faith why doſt thou doubt?</hi> Yet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104398:4"/>
after this <hi>Peters</hi> faith was ſhaken. Again when that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples could not cure the man that was Lunatick, then Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto them, <hi>O faithleſſe and perverſe generation, how long ſhall I be with you? how long ſhall I ſuffer you? bring him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to me;</hi> And one of the Diſciples ſaid, <hi>why could not we caſt him out?</hi> Then Jeſus ſaid unto them, <hi>becauſe of your unbelief, For verily I ſay unto you, if you had faith as a grain of muſtard-ſeed, you ſhould ſay unto this mountain remove hence to yonder place, and it ſhould be ſo, and nothing ſhall be unpoſſible unto you;</hi> And unto <hi>Thomas</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Be not faithleſſe but believing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here is the very life of your life, that you believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for <hi>whoſoever believeth on him ſhall not be aſhamed, for there is no difference between the</hi> Jew <hi>and the</hi> Greek, <hi>for the ſame Lord over all is rich unto all that call upon him and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo now Friends, ſeeing that many when tryals come upon them have been ſhaken, as you may ſee in the Scriptures more fully, Therefore in the fear of the Lord God keep cloſe and near to the word of faith which is nigh in the heart, and neither aſcend nor deſcend, but keep to the righteouſneſſe of faith, and then you keep to the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and to the Evidence and Teſtimony of things not ſeen. Through faith you may underſtand that the Worlds were made by the Inviſible Word of God, ſo that things which are ſeen are not made of things which do appear, but by the immortal and Eternal Word which was in the beginning, here you wil ſee him that is inviſible, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did who believed, and it was accounted unto him for Righteouſneſſe, not when he was in the Circumciſion, but when he was in the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and ſo he received the ſigne of Circumciſion a ſeal of the righteouſneſſe of his faith which he had before he was Circumciſed, that he might be the Father of all that believe though they be not Circumciſed outwardly, that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe might be imputed unto them alſo, not of the Jews onely but alſo of the Gentiles; for all who walk in the ſteps of that faith of our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> for the promiſe that he ſhould be the Heir of the World was, not to <hi>Abraham</hi> or to his ſeed through the Law, but through the Righteouſneſſe of Faith, therefore is it of faith that it might be by Grace,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104398:4"/>
to the end that the promiſe might be ſure to all the ſeed, not to that onely which is of the Law, but to that alſo which is of the faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> which is the Father of us all, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope believed in hope, that he might become the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of many Nations: Oh the Infinite love and wiſdom of the Lord God, and the depth of the myſtery that hath been hid but now is revealed by his Spirit.</p>
            <p>Know ye therefore that they that are of faith are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Scripture which cannot be broken foreſeeing that God would Juſtifie the Heathen through faith preached before the Goſpel unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying <hi>in thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed:</hi> The promiſe of the bleſſing to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, this is the glad tydings of the Everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the liberty to the Captives, the deſire of all Nations which is now come and riſen, manifeſted and fulfilled what he hath promiſed in this his day; And all they that be of the faith are bleſſed with faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> and this is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel which the Apoſtle was not aſhamed of to preach, which is the power of God unto ſalvation to every one that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, to the Jew firſt and alſo to the Greek, for therein is the Righteouſneſſe of God revealed from faith to faith, for the Juſt lives by faith, whether they be Jew or Greek, bond or free, there is neither male nor female here but they are all one in Chriſt Jeſus: And if they be Chriſts then are they <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> ſeed and heirs according to promiſe. And here is the fountain opened for the houſe of <hi>David</hi> and for the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for ſin and for uncleanneſſe, Chriſt Jeſus the Everlaſting Covenant, who in the laſt day of the great feaſt ſtood and cryed, ſaying, <hi>If any man were athirſt let him come unto me and drink, he that believeth on me out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of living waters,</hi> but this he ſpake of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which they that believed on him ſhould receive, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the words of the Apoſtle, who ſaid unto the Jews, <hi>Received you the Spirit by the works of the Law or by the hearing of faith?</hi> for we through the ſpirit wait for the hope of the Righteouſneſſe of faith, for in Chriſt Jeſus neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth, but faith that worketh by Love, and obedience unto him, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and Life, he that believeth on me, though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104398:5"/>
he was dead yet ſhall he live;</hi> And he that liveth and believeth ſhall never die, and he that believeth worketh the works of God, he that believeth ſhall never thirſt; And this is the will of the Father that hath ſent the Son, that every one that ſeeth him, ſhould believe on him and have everlaſting life, and he would raiſe him up at the laſt day; and bleſſed are they that believes and lives in the freedom of the ſpirit, for to the ſpiritual mind is life and peace, and no evil tyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings can come to ſuch, ſuch reckons not the ſufferings of this preſent time worthy to be compared to the glory that ſhal be revealed, for the Juſt lives by his Faith, but if any man draw back, my ſoul hath no pleaſure in him.</p>
            <p>Now Friends, ſeeing it is ſo, that the ſpirit ſpeaketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the Faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits and Doctrines of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and that ſome have caſt off their firſt Faith, and ſome through the love of money have erred from the Faith, and pierced themſelves through with many ſorrows, and ſome have denyed the Faith, and ſome have had their Faith over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by others words, and ſome have made ſhipwrack of Faith, and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of many (and ſundry) that fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and loſt their firſt love, and did not keep their firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as you may read; And therefore did he exhort them that they ſhould earneſtly contend for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints?</p>
            <p>And ſo Friends, this is the very end of my writing, that you even would contend for the pretious Faith in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and alſo in the general; And call to mind how that God after he had brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> yet they fell in the Wilderneſſe becauſe of unbelief; Therefore fly all ungodlineſs and follow after Righteouſneſs, Faith, Love and Patience, fight the good fight of Faith and lay hold on eternal Life; Conſider the Apoſtle and High Prieſt of our profeſſion, Chriſt Jeſus, who was faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful in all his houſe as a Servant, and Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe, whoſe houſe are we, if we hold faſt the confidence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of our hope unto the end, here will every one be preſerved clear in his condition, who through the Spirit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104398:5"/>
wait for the hope of the Righteouſneſſe of Faith, and take heed there be not in any of you an evil heart of unbelief departing from the Living God, for we are made partakers of Chriſt if we hold faſt the profeſſion of our Faith without wavering; And unto us the Goſpel is preached as well as unto them, but the word preached did not profit them not being mixed with Faith in them that had it, Therefore did he ſwear in his wrath that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, they entered not becauſe of unbelief.</p>
            <p>Now this being ſo fully proved and manifeſted to you, lay aſide every weight, and run with patience the Race that is ſet before you, looking unto Jeſus the Authour and finiſher of our Faith, who is the Corner ſtone and Rock of Eternal ſalvation, who is rooted and grounded on him will not be ſhaken though the ſtorms and tempeſts beat; Conſider him that endured ſuch contradiction of ſinners, leaſt you be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; faint in your minds; For all the promiſes of God in him are Yea and in him Amen, in whom we have boldneſſe and acceſſe with confidence by the Faith of him who worketh all in us and for us; For none are Juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, and by Faith you ſtand, For God hath put no difference betwixt the Jews and the Gentiles, if their hearts be purified by Faith, whoſe eyes are opened, and who are turned from the darkneſſe to the ligbt, from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive the forgiveneſſe of ſin, and an Inheritance among them that are ſanctified by Faith in Chriſt, even the Righteouſneſſe of God which is by Faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all them that believe, For there is no difference, for all have ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God; For if the firſt fruit be holy, the Lump is holy alſo, and if the Root be holy ſo are the branches, and if ſome of the branches be broken off, it is becauſe of unbelief, and thou ſtandeſt by Faith, be not high-minded but fear.</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, conſider that your ſtanding is by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, even we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be Juſtified by the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>For whatſoever is born of God overcometh the World, and this is the victory that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the world, even our faith, who is he that overcometh the world,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104398:6"/>
but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> here ſhall we be more then Conquerors, as we abide and grow from ſtrength to ſtrength, and from Faith to Faith, building up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our moſt holy Faith, till we all come in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, that we henceforth be no more Children toſſed to and fro and carried about with every winde of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men and cunning craftineſſe whereby they lye in wait to deceive, but ſpeaking the Truth in love may grow into him in all things who is the head, even Chriſt, that ſo we might make all men ſee what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery which from the beginning of the World hath been hid in God, who Created all things by Jeſus Chriſt, in whom we have boldneſſe and acceſſe with confidence by the Faith in him, that ſo Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by Faith, and you being rooted and grounded in love may be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the height, breadth, length and depth, and to know the Love of God which paſſeth knowledge, unto whom be eternal glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dominion for ever.</p>
            <p>Now dearly beloved Friends and Brethren, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, take unto you the Armour of Righteouſneſſe, that you may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil, For now you come not to wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with fleſh and blood, but with principalities and powers, and againſt the Rulers of the darkneſſe of this World, and againſt ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places; Wherefore let your clothing and Armour be Light, that you may be able to ſtand in the evil day: and above all take the ſhield of Faith, in this will you quench the fiery darts of the wicked: Stand faſt in one ſpirit ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing terrified by your Adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of Salvation and that of God; For unto you is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not onely to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake, and that you holding faſt the Word of Life, may cauſe us to rejoyce in the day of Chriſt that we have not run in vain, neither laboured in vain; Yea if I were offered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104398:6"/>
upon the ſacrifice of your Faith, I could joy and rejoyce with you all. And now that you may come to the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the firſt born from the dead, that you being rooted and grounded in him, and that through the ſpirit you may wait for the hope of Righteouſneſſe by Faith, and ſo grow up as living plants, which are called Trees of Righteouſneſs the planting of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And truly Friends, there is none that believes but he knows that God is, nor there is none that believes but he hath the witneſſe in him that he is in the unity of the Faith, and he that believes hath his heart purified by faith, he that believes is entered into the reſt, and he is ſealed with the ſpirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>So Friends ſearch your ſelves, for a ſinner in <hi>Zion</hi> will be afraid, and fear will ſupprize the Hypocrite, and truly none can dwell with the everlaſting burning but he that worketh Righteouſneſſe, and every mans work muſt be tryed by fire, and he that is ſaved in the day of the Lord it is ſo as by fire, it is not offerings that will burn that will ſerve in this our day, but it is the perfect offering of Righteouſneſs that will paſſe the fire that is now accepted. The God of Eternal power and life ſtrengthen you by his Grace in the Inward man, that ſo you may be True and Faithful War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours in the Work of the Lord, that you may fight the good fight, and finiſh your courſe, and keep the Faith, that a crown of Righteouſneſſe may be laid up for you.</p>
            <p>For certainly the day is come in which the Lord with his ſore great and ſtrong ſword will he puniſh <hi>Leviathan</hi> that piercing crooked Serpent, and he will ſlay the Dragon that is in the Sea; And though there be a Song of a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of red Wine, yet the Lord will keep his Plants, he will water it every moment leaſt any hurt it, yea he will keep it night and day, if Bryars and Thorns be ſet in battel againſt him, he will go through them and burn them together, for the Lords people is his portion, <hi>Iſrael</hi> is the lot of his Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, and though he hath found <hi>Jacob</hi> in a Deſert Land, and a waſt howling Wilderneſs, yet he hath led him about and inſtructed him, he hath kept him as the Apple of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104398:7"/>
eye, as an Eagle ſtirreth up her Neaſt, fluttereth over her young, ſpreadeth abroad her Wings and taketh them, ſo doth the Lord with the Seed of his Covenant; And the day is come that they do ſing in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> the Lyon of which Tribe hath opened the Book and unlooſed the Seals; We have a ſtrong City, Salvation God hath given for Walls and Bulwarks, the Gates whereof are opened that the Righteous Nation may enter in, who are as lively Stones built up a Spiritual houſe, an Holy Prieſthood to offer up Spiritual Sacrifice acceptable unto God by Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe foundation is laid in <hi>Zion</hi> the chief corner ſtone elect and pretious, and he that believeth on him ſhall never be confounded, unto all that believe on him he is pretious, but unto them which be diſobedient, the Stone which the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders diſallowed, the ſame is made the head of the Corner, and you that do believe on him are the choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſthood, an Holy Nation, a peculiar People, ſo will you ſhew forth the praiſes of him that hath called you out of darkneſſe into his marvelous Light, here abiding with God, whoſe immortalty dwells in the Light, and whoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſweet precious preſence is in the Light, here abiding with God, whoſe immortality dwells in the Light, and whoſe power and ſweet pretious preſence is in the Light all things here are poſſible, here will you inherit all things, ſo while you have the Light, believe in the Light, that you may be the Children of the Light begotten into it, born of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is light, here you will be preſerved ſitting under your own vine, where none can make you affraid, while that <hi>Babylon</hi> is falling, and all the graven Images of her Gods is breaking unto the ground, <hi>I will riſe up</hi> ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts, <hi>and will cut off from</hi> Babylon <hi>the Name and Remnant, Son and Nephew</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will make it a poſſeſſion for the Bittern, and I will ſweep it with the beſome of deſtruction;</hi> The Lord of Hoſts hath ſworn ſaying, <hi>Surely as I have thought ſo ſhall it come to paſs, as I have purpoſed ſo ſhall it ſtand, that I will break the</hi> Syrian <hi>in my land, and upon my Mountains tread him under foot, then ſhall his yoak depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their ſhouldiers;</hi> This is the purpoſe that is purpoſed upon the whole earth, and this is the hand
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104398:7"/>
that is ſtretched out upon all Nations, for the Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed, and who ſhall diſannul it? And his hand is ſtretched out, and who ſhall turn it back? So all wait in the Faith of Gods Elect for the fulfilling &amp; bringing to paſs of his great Work, for God is faithful that hath promiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham,</hi> before him whom he believed, even God who quickeneth the dead, and calleth thoſe things which be not, as though they were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> againſt hope believed in hope, and ſo was the Father of many Nations, he ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God through unbelife, but was ſtrong in Faith giving God the Glory, and this was counted to him for Righteouſneſs; Now ye that ſeek the Lord, ye that follow after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ye muſt look unto the Rock whence ye were hewen, and to the hole of the Rock whence ye were digged, ye muſt look unto <hi>Abraham</hi> your Father in the Faith and unto <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> Womb who bare you, <hi>For I have called him alone</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have bleſſed him and increaſed him,</hi> here is <hi>Zion</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and the waſt places and Wilderneſſes made like <hi>Eden,</hi> and her deſarts like the Garden of the Lord, joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is found therein, Thankſgiving and the voice of Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to this ſafe habitation of reſt and peace which is eternal and doth endure for ever, do I commit you.</p>
            <p>The believing <hi>Jews</hi> and the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> are the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and are bleſſed with faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> for of a truth God is no reſpecter of perſons, but every one that believeth and worketh Righteouſneſſe is accepted of him, whether they be <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Greeks, Barbarian</hi> or <hi>Cythian,</hi> Bond or Free, if they believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and walk in him they are all one, and this is the Salvation that is to the ends of the Earth the Covenant of Light.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104398:8"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>FAith is the ſubstance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen, though many profeſſe it, yet they are but few that know the excellency of it; In the World there are profeſſions of Faith many, and great Diſputings and Contentions about it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all ſorts of Profeſſors; Nevertheleſſe when the Son of man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on Earth among <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi> that doth not believe in the light which he hath enlightned them withal? I ſay nay, for though many have the words from which they have heard a report of him, yet ſhall they not thereby be justified, neither every one that ſaith he believeth the words, and is not yet come to hear and obey the word nigh in the Heart (by the hearing of which Faith cometh) though ſuch may profeſſe faith in words, yet in the day of tryal (I do aver) that their faith will never avail nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit them; For that faith which purifies the heart, which giveth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the World, through which Kingdoms were ſubdued, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe wrought, promiſes obtained, the mouths of Lyons ſtopped, the violence of the Fire quenched, the edge of the Sword eſcaped, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, That that Faith by which thoſe things have been brought to paſs was the gift of God, and Chriſt the Light of the World, the Son of Gods Love was the Author of it, and they whoſe Faith stands in the Power of God, who have received Gods gift, and have believed in Chriſt the Light, the Author and finiſher of the Saints Faith, ſuch can give an account of the Effects of their Faith which worketh by love, through which they have gotten victory over their Corruptions and Lusts, over Sin and Death, over the World and him that is the God of it, and by which they have paſſed through many perils and dangers both by Sea and Land; And when the Lord hath moved them to go unto a people in weakneſſe fear and much trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, they not knowing what they ſhould ſay unto them, or whether they ſhould eſcape with their lives or no, yet they have given up, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104398:8"/>
by Faith have been made ſtrong in the Power of the Lords might, and through Faith they have received the word of the Lord plentiouſly, &amp; have miniſtred it powerfully in the demonſtration of the ſpirit; and by faith they have eſcaped the hands of unreaſonable men, and often have turned to flight the Armies of the <hi>Aliens,</hi> as witneſſe the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent flying of the Hireling Prieſts and their Adherents before a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed people, who eſteem the reproach of Chriſt greater riches then the Treaſures of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who to this day ſuſtains tryals of cruel mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſome ſcourgings, and many Bonds and Impriſonment, who by their patience and long ſuffering have obtained through faith a good report, yea joy and gladneſse in the midſt of their tribulation; They have ſeen through faith many high and mighty Mountains re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way, and cast into the Sea, And they have alſo heard and ſeen the Sea rage and ſwell and make a great noiſe, which they have ſeen through faith ſtilled, and the waters thereof on heaps hurled; Yea through faith they have paſſed through many Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and fiery Tryals, through many Perils and Dangers, through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hardſhips and Difficulties, and now (through mercy) have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the end of their faith, to wit, the Salvation of their Souls, and of this ſort are they that know the excellency of Faith and the worth of it; others that profeſſe faith in words (who do not believe in the Light which hath enlightned them withal) may aſſay to go through the things which the Righteous paſs through, but let ſuch take heed that they be not ſwallowed up by them as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were (who wanted Faith in God) yet aſſayed to follow the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> through the Sea, but behold they were drowned, when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by Faith paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through, as by dry land, ſo without faith we may conclude it is impoſſible to pleaſe God or to come unto God, or unto the rest which God hath prepared for his people, which many aſsayes and ſtrives to enter into, but cannot by reaſon of unbelief; So let all the faithful that ſtands by Faith be circumſpect and vigilant, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand, that through faith you may obtain an incorruptible inheritance which will never fade away.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>the 3th, moneth, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:104398:9"/>
            <head>Errours eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Page 3. <hi>l.</hi> 10. blot out <hi>the,</hi> pag. 4. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for the ſtate which we muſt paſs through, read, the ſtate which muſt be paſſed through, p. 9. l. 7. for had r. heard, p. 11. l. 32 for plants r. plant, p. 12. l. 19. about two lines are to be raced out, p. 15. l. 22. hath enlightned, r. Chriſt hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104398:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
